This domain covers code documentation and
structure. In this domain, we will see how
to document code, and then we will see how to
structure functions, which allow for blocks of
code to be reused as needed. The first piece of
structure we will cover is that of indentation.
As we have seen in many topics up to this point,
any block of code that runs as part of a loop or
conditional statement needs to be indented.
This indentation structure sets Python apart
from other languages. With most other languages,
these code blocks are inside curly brackets,
and indentation is used merely to make code more
readable. To further illustrate the importance
of indentation, I am reusing a code example
from earlier in the course, one with a lot of
indentation. This file, 411-indentation,
has a while loop, and everything inside
the while loop is indented. Inside the while
loop, we have a for loop and an if statement,
and the code under each block is also indented.
Besides generating error messages if code is not
indented properly, let’s see where indentation
can affect code logic. I will run this code,
and the print statement on line 8 prints only
once because it is not part of any loop. However,
if I indent this to fit under the while loop and
rerun the code, the print statement prints each
time this while loop iterates. This behavior
is not the app's intent, so I will move the
print statement back outside of the while loop.
The amount of indentation we have within a code
example like this does affect code logic, so
we need to make sure what needs to go into a
loop is indented under it and, more importantly,
what needs to be outside loops is not indented,
lest we get bad results with code. I have
saved some critical aspects of indentation for
last. First, you need to be consistent with your
indentation. Four spaces is the recommended amount
per indentation level. You can use the Tab key on
the keyboard to indent lines, but whatever you do,
be consistent. Watch what happens if I vary an
indent inside of the while loop. Immediately,
the code editor has a tooltip message that
tells us the indent amounts are inconsistent.
Having inconsistent indentation will lead to
syntax errors, which we will cover elsewhere
in the course. Second, beginning with Python 3,
mixing tabs and spaces in a single block is not
allowed. This is because Python considers tabs
and spaces as different characters even though
they might look the same in your text editor.
Lastly, some text editors like Notepad++ offer
settings to automatically convert tabs to spaces
for better consistency. Because tabs and spaces
are invisible characters, you may need to enable
a setting to view all symbols to identify them.